# **Alan Russell**

## Senior Full Stack Engineer

🔁 ajrussellaudio@gmail.com 📞 07519003922 📊 alan-russell 🌎 ajrussellaudio

## PROFILE

Software developer with exceptional problem-solving skills, focused on highquality web products. Expert in creating intuitive, clean, tested, and maintainable front-end interfaces using JavaScript and React, with a strong understanding of back-end technologies. Experienced leader and mentor in high-level decisionmaking, professional development, and team empowerment.



#### React

NextJS, Vite, React Native, React Query, React Testing Library, React Hook Form, Redux, Framer Motion

#### Front end JavaScript

TypeScript, Svelte, RxJS, D3, Tone.js, p5.js, Web Audio API

#### **CSS**

Tailwind, Bootstrap, Sass, CSS Modules, Styled Components,

#### Back end JavaScript

Node, Express, Nest.js, Prisma, Sanity, GraphQL, REST, PostgreSQL, MongoDB

#### **Team leadership**

Mentoring, requirements gathering, architecture, collaboration with UX researchers and designers, stakeholder management, one-to-ones, professional development, recruitment

### ...and the rest!

Python, Django, Flask, Ruby, Ruby on Rails, Sinatra, Java, Spring Boot, C#, .NET, SuperCollider,

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Lead Front End Engineer (Contract), Pickatale ₽

March 2024 – September 2024 | Oslo, Norway

React, TypeScript, Next.js, Nest.js, GraphQL Lead a cross-functional team for the Library product, delivering a complete visual redesign, SSR, performance and accessibility enhancements, and integration with Pickatale Create (generative AI). Also responsible for project management, maintenance of legacy products, and coaching and mentoring team members.

#### Instructor (Contract), CodeClan

August 2023 - November 2023 | Glasgow, Scotland JavaScript, React, MongoDB, Java, Spring, PostgreSQL, **TypeScript** 

After the company's liquidation, I reconnected with CodeClan to deliver essential content to the final Glasgow cohorts.

#### Senior Full Stack Engineer, Orri &

December 2022 - May 2023 | London, England React, TypeScript, Next.js, Tailwind, Ruby on Rails At this eating disorder clinic, I introduced TypeScript and built a UI design system following a rebrand. I added automated testing in a CI/CD pipeline, cutting down on failed deployments and increasing developer velocity.

## Senior Full Stack Engineer, Pickatale

December 2021 - December 2022 | Oslo, Norway

React, TypeScript, Next.js, Svelte, Nest.js, Express I led a cross-functional team modernizing a children's book content editor. I actively contributed to architectural decisions, collaborated with product owners, designers and researchers, and played a key role in developing the customer-facing website.

## Senior Front End Developer, Digirati ∂

November 2020 – December 2021 | Glasgow, Scotland React, TypeScript, Next.js, Django, .NET

## PROJECTS

## Rhythmetic ∂

2020

React, RxJS, Bulma, Sass
I work on many niche projects connected
to music production but this has been the
most popular. Rhythmetic is a collection
of calculators for working with audio
samples in a given tempo, frequency or
musical pitch.

## Flexbox Froggy

2018

JavaScript, jQuery, CSS, SVG
This online game was part of a CodeClan homework assignment, and I enhanced it by adding a "colourblind mode," replacing colours with patterns. This not only helped a colourblind student but improved accessibility for all players. My contribution was merged, improving the game's accessibility and expanding the reach to a wider audience.

## **EDUCATION**

Software Development Certificate, CodeClan, Edinburgh, Scotland

July 2016 - November 2016

Audio Engineering Diploma, SAE Institute, Glasgow, Scotland ∂

April 2009 - April 2010

BSc Audio Technology with Electronics, Glasgow Caledonian University *∂* 

August 1999 - May 2003

I led UI development in cultural heritage and digital archiving for clients like the Wellcome Collection and Harvard University. Introduced key enhancements, including UI code unit testing and user testing, resulting in improved project outcomes and team efficiency. Provided oversight, mentorship, and code review for junior developers and backend engineers in modern front-end development techniques.

## Senior Web Developer, Twig Science ∂

June 2019 – November 2020 | Glasgow, Scotland React, Node, PostgreSQL, GraphQL, Apollo, Prisma | started as a mid-level contributor, and earned an internal promotion to senior role. I led UI development for a toprated educational platform for American schools with a 40% market share in California and other states. I guided architectural decisions and provided crucial mentorship to junior developers, ensuring team success.

#### Front End Developer, Arnold Clark @

December 2018 – May 2019 | Glasgow, Scotland React, React Native, Next.js, Ruby on Rails | led a team composed of junior developers and apprentices in successfully delivering significant features on the customer-facing website and mobile app of a prominent national car retailer.

#### React Developer (Contract), Waracle ∂

July 2018 – December 2018 | Glasgow, Scotland React, Redux, RxJS

I revamped user authentication in a popular banking app, and prototyped a customer account portal for global energy markets.

#### Instructor, CodeClan

November 2016 – July 2018 | Glasgow, Scotland JavaScript (Node, React), Ruby (Sinatra, Rails), Java (Android), Python (Flask)

At this digital skills academy I led curriculum creation on front-end topics like JavaScript and CSS, and delivered lessons across the full stack of web development. Our team guided 120 students toward entry-level software roles, and I found immense satisfaction in fostering future talent.

## **Audio Engineer (Freelance)**

2004 - 2016

Pro Tools, Logic, Ableton, NI Komplete, MPC, Elektron, modular synths...

Before switching career to software development, I worked in various jobs in the music industry, predominantly as a live sound engineer and in equipment sales.